We all want to eat
the kinds of foods
that make us feel
better and live longer.
But there’s so much conflicting
information out there,
so many nutrition opinions.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast,
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
It’s my job to give you
the information you need
to make the healthiest
choices possible.
In the beginning,
there was angiogenesis,
the creation of blood vessels.
Tumors use it to keep growing.
And as it turns out,
our fatty tissue also
needs it to expand.
So, might an anti-angiogenic approach
work for weight loss too?
Many of our modern front-line
therapies against cancer incorporate
anti-angiogenesis strategies,
from the Greek words
"angio" meaning vessel,
and "genesis" meaning creation.
So anti-angiogenesis is opposing
the creation of blood vessels.
In other words, fighting cancer
by cutting off tumor supply lines.
Some cancers are only able to
grow to about the size of a tip
of a ballpoint pen
without a blood supply.
Tumor growth then stalls.
Autopsy studies show
that virtually everyone
has these tiny tumors
in them by age 70.
Cancer without disease
can, therefore,
be considered the normal
state during aging.
To commandeer a blood supply,
tumors diabolically release
angiogenic factors,
chemicals that cause
new blood vessels to
sprout towards the cancer.
Once a blood vessel reaches
the tumor and attaches,
it's off to the races ---
the tumor can then
take off exponentially.
By starving cancer
of its blood supply,
chemotherapy that
blocks this process
can sometimes cause
tumors to shrink,
but ideally, we wouldn't have
to wait until such a late stage
to nip them in the bud.
That's where our diet
can come in.
Many of the phytonutrients
we know and love in tea, spices,
berries, broccoli, and beans
have anti-angiogenic properties.
Given the power of plants,
the foundation
of an anti-angiogenic
approach to cancer
has been considered
a whole food plant-based diet.
But the title of this video is
"Targeting Angiogenesis
to Lose Weight."
What does this have
to do with obesity?
Well, think about it.
Tumors aren't the only tissue
in the body with
expanding volume.
The average tumor picked
up by mammograms
is only about the
size of a marble,
and it can take breast cancer
decades to grow.
Whereas overfeed people
and you can easily add
an entire pound of fatty tissue
in a matter of days.
And body fat is highly vascularized.
Each fat cell in our body
is essentially surrounded
by tiny blood vessels.
In large liposuction operations,
a third of what's vacuumed
out is straight blood.
Throughout adulthood, our fatty
tissue is constantly remodeling,
expanding and shrinking, based
on our day-to-day energy demand.
This requires the
development and retreat
of extensive networks
of new blood vessels.
The human body already contains
60,000 miles of blood vessels.
Imagine how many more miles
have to be constructed
when we gain weight.
Without angiogenesis,
without the sprouting of
all these new blood vessels,
we wouldn't be able
to add all that fat.
Now, do you see
where this is all going?
To expand, fat cells release
the same kinds of chemicals
that tumors do
to swell its blood supply.
Fatty tissue is so angiogenic,
open-heart surgeons have even
tried grafting fatty tissue directly
on the heart after a heart attack
in hopes it would foster the growth
of arteries to bypass the blockages.
You can take fat samples from obese
individuals during bariatric surgery,
place them on living membranes
of fertile chicken eggs,
and within a week the fat is
literally engulfed in blood vessels.
That may help explain
why excess body fat
can accelerate cancer growth.
Obesity increases the risk of more
than a dozen different cancers,
increasing the overall
risk of getting
and then dying from cancer
by about 20%.
All those angiogenic factors
released from our increasing body fat
may spill out into our bloodstream,
resulting in higher blood levels
among overweight individuals,
which can then drop back down
when we lose weight.
So maybe we could get
the best of both worlds
if we treated obesity like a tumor,
using anti-angiogenic strategies
to prevent the expansion of
our fat mass in the first place.
There are anti-angiogenic drugs,
as well as anti-angiogenic foods.
We'll explore both, next.
Body fat is probably the most
highly vascularized tissue
in the body, meaning it has
the most blood vessels.
In fact, each individual
fat cell is surrounded
by an extensive network
of tiny blood vessels.
And since the formation
of these blood vessels
appears to play a critical role
in fatty tissue growth
and reduction,
the regulation of angiogenesis,
the blood vessel
formation process,
may contribute to weight
gain and weight loss.
So researchers tried injecting
anti-angiogenic drugs
into overfed lab animals
and were able to induce
profound weight loss in mice
as well as in nonhuman primates,
which is how scientists
often refer to monkeys.
The problem is that
anti-angiogenic drugs
can cause a variety of rare
but fatal side effects.
We may be willing
to accept those risks
in the context
of cancer treatment,
but when it comes to cancer
prevention or obesity,
anti-angiogenic diets
would seem a safer bet ---
not to mention cheaper:
anti-angiogenic drugs
can cost $6,000 per dose.
So which foods are the
most anti-angiogenic?
It's interesting how they figured
out that dietary components
could be anti-angiogenic at all.
Realizing that those eating
plant-based diets were protected
from diseases of excess
angiogenesis like cancer
and diabetic vision loss,
researchers took a group
of plant-based eaters
and started pitting various
components of their urine
against the growth of
human blood vessel cells
harvested from discarded
umbilical cords.
The concentration of
phytonutrients in the urine
of vegetarians can
be 30 times higher
than that of the
general population.
Using this method,
they identified a number
of natural anti-angiogenic
compounds in our diet.
The question then became
could the levels required
to block angiogenesis
in a petri dish be reached
in the bloodstream
after eating a meal?
The answer, researchers
soon realized, is yes.
Anti-angiogenic concentrations
of broccoli compounds
can be reached in the
bloodstream within an hour,
eating less than three-quarters
of a cup of broccoli soup.
So these are totally doable
kinds of quantities.
You'll note most of these
compounds may be cleared
from our body within
6 hours, though,
and fall back to nearly
zero within 24 hours,
so we should strive to eat
cruciferous vegetables
at least once a day.
Anti-angiogenic concentrations
of beta-cryptoxanthin can be
reached within hours of eating
two cups of red-fleshed papaya.
One and a quarter cup
of boiled onions may get you
an anti-angiogenic
dose of quercetin
circulating in your blood
in less than an hour.
The level of protective
soybean compounds
that may be necessary
has been found
in the bloodstream of those
eating ordinary Japanese diets.
Now, I'm not dreaming
up some sort
of broccoli-papaya-
onion-tofu casserole.
These are just examples showing
anti-angiogenic concentrations
can be achieved within
your bloodstream
after eating a reasonable
serving size.
In general, the most concentrated
dietary sources of polyphenols,
the class of phytonutrients
containing many
of the anti-angiogenic
compounds discovered to date,
are herbs and spices.
The only others to
place in the top ten
(out of more than
450 foods tested)
were berries, cocoa powder,
and ground flaxseed.
On a per-serving basis, most of
the top contenders are berries,
with artichokes
leading the vegetables
and whole grain rye
leading the grains.
Ironically, yogurt is a leading
source in the United States,
but only because most
are fruit-flavored,
with many containing
berries as ingredients,
whereas even plain soy yogurt
makes it into the top 25.
For cancer prevention,
researchers suggest
the constant consumption
of anti-angiogenic foods.
Do we have evidence that
it's having an effect?
Well, based on the analysis
of more than a thousand tumors
from one of Harvard's studies
on male health professionals,
men eating the most tomato
products had significantly less
angiogenesis within their tumor,
which then appeared to translate
into a reduced risk
of fatal disease.
Yeah, but would the same
anti-angiogenic potential
of fruits and vegetables also help
keep our bellies from growing?
There's only one way to find out.
A meta-analysis of more than a
dozen randomized controlled trials
of fruits and vegetable
interventions for
overweight individuals found
6 extra pounds of weight loss,
but that could be from
a whole variety of factors,
like decreased calorie density
from the fiber and water content,
but maybe angiogenesis
inhibition is playing a role.
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
go to the NutritionFacts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
My last two books are
“How to Survive a Pandemic”
and my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
Get ready this year for the
launch of How Not to Age.
And, of course, all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes
directly to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
with bite-sized videos and articles
uploaded nearly every day.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorships,
no kickbacks.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to
my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.